foreign hypothetical
hypothetical
that can be very practical
say a save humans
save humans
were to have
a transparent skin
so when we look at each other we see
what's inside
when you look at someone's face you see
the skull the brain everything you see
the layers like
would people
then still
be attracted to each other physically
essentially yes yes
why
because you would still look for safety
for pleasure you would still attend to
the beautiful rather than
but what is beautiful if I you know you
look at somebody and you see feces
inside of them while you talk to them
you would would that be beautiful no
what would determine beautiful is
beautiful
maybe somebody could have a beautiful
skull
well but what will make it beautiful
see the answer is correct yes people
would still be attracted to but the
reasons you gave not because of that
distracting from
no that's not that's not quite the
reason people don't seek sensuality
because they want to be distracted
there's another reason more fundamental
more primordial reason for people
seeking Central gratification what is
that
avoidance of the disgusting
how's that felt
how is the avoidance how is the
disgusting felt that's not unpleasant so
for as long as the mind doesn't know any
other Escape From Pain they'll find
sensuality even in the most disgusting
things or on a practical level
or on a practical level
you can have
all the discussed around you if your
mind is not developed in regard to your
own body
a lost attraction everything else will
find its way
so exactly then you would like the shape
of the skull of these corpse and so on
because so what does that mean as a suit
to say for as long as a monk is not
developed in regard to his own body he
will be attracted to the you know the
central objects so that's it's that lack
of development in regard to your own
body that
makes beautiful beautiful makes
beautiful Central so to speak makes it
um
sort of
inviting and valuable for seeking
gratification it's not the essential
objects it's not essential objects
exactly so you can have a skull
that can be taken essentially and you
see it's beautiful features but there
are also the ugly features that you're
ignoring so the point of like the reason
what I'm saying is the reason you would
be ignoring the obvious and just picking
on the beautiful aspects secondary
aspects and making them primary is
because you're not developed in regard
to your own body and what does that mean
being developed or not developed what
does that mean so how would one say we
all have translucent skin
you see the disgust of the Natural Body
for what it is you see through you see
what it carries it is just a bag of skin
with all these different things inside
and now you can see through it as well
so you can't ignore it
yet you still find your mind seeking
gratification in those disgusting things
and now you heard it's because you
haven't developed yourself in regard to
your own body
so what does that entail how do you
develop yourself in regarding body
learn to endure the pressure of sites
so sense restraint in virtue first so
you don't act out of
you don't allow basically actions that
would allow body to seek the pleasure so
you restrain the body
you restrain the speech and so on okay
so that's the first step
that's how the mind
begins its own development in regard to
this body what else then do we do
being touched by a pleasant feeling
by a possibility of gratification that
is already felt
uplifting delightful escaping this
confinement of this body
that's enough for you to not be
developed in regard to it obviously that
possibility of gratification like
literally you can use this body to
experience pleasure
so first you have to stop doing that
in order to see where that whole
experience and that Prospect and the
possibility is rooted and it's rooted
simply in yeah body on its own
it's quite neutral something compared to
it's kind of burdening in a way
so for as long as you value the
possibility of gratification as a means
of escape from that natural burden of
this body your mind will not be
developed in regard to the body
why do you need to escape sorry why do
you need to escape
because you don't start from a neutral
position you start is only dependent on
the pleasures so that's you know that's
your reference from that point of view
neutral body is unbearable unpleasant
it's unpleasant yeah
so sensory strain needs to be done first
so you actually step outside of that
water to recognize what the dry ground
is and then eventually you can dry up
yourself so you can have as I said zombies
so you can have as I said zombies
walking around you
but basically if you still value
the possibility of gratification through
this body and these senses last we'll
find a way you will find something
attractive sooner or later when the edge
presents itself one way or the other so
when the age does present itself if you
have been sense restrained and now
recognize it as a state of the body that
must be endured not fed further you are
actually developing your mind in regard
to your own body
that's what he says in the sutthism I
mean like the development of the Mind
does not come through meditation
technique sensation or nostril watching
comes on account of purification of
virtue having purified The Virtue he
then purifies his mind through that
so all those subtler intentions of what
you value what you want what you act
towards become apparent by not acting
out of unwholesome intention on the
level of the mind he purifies his mind
so purification of virtue leads to
purification of mind that then leads to
purification of views
it then leads to purification of
knowledge and vision and Liberation and
everything else
the same I guess with the well the same
principle applies in terms of
um
you'll always want to get rid of yeah
this this
burden of the body by Yeah by resisting
whatever's you find
disagreeable basically disagreeable is
confining just unpleasant feeling is a form of
just unpleasant feeling is a form of
confinement
so for as long as you value the escape
by the means of replacing it with
another feeling you will not be free
from sensuality and your mind will not
be developed in regard to your body and
that's why you said for the Buddha that
he found the Escape within confinement
his teaching is the escape not replacing
the confinement with something else
but Escape within it so if there is an
unpleasant feeling well you escaped it
while it's there not because you
replaced it with pleasure if you're
touched by Pleasant feeling you escaped
it while it's there not because you
acted out of it towards more pleasure if
there is a neutral feeling you escaped
it by understanding it
come on that was pretty much exactly
what I was going to
um bring up was a
there's the
the
burden of confinement is actually what
you have to see is that that the reason
it's felt this confining
is not because it's actually because of
this um
trying to escape really because
of trying to escape which is actually
the more you resist the more parent the
more heavy the more confining your
experience becomes and that's in regard
to both like equally the the pleasure or
the relief of uh experiencing essential
pleasure is determined by the degree of
the itch in the same way which is a
confinement which is a confinement in
the same way as like even in a mundane
sense let's say being released from a
debt or being released from prison is
determined by the degrees of which the
dash was causing you worry and burden
and so it's like that's kind of mundane
relief that can't be a relief because
it's within them and that's where people
like even in nature of sensuality people
enjoy Central pleasures
if they were harder to obtain they would
be sweeter so to speak
because yeah the confinement has been
built up
but fundamentally you need to recognize
that your way out of confinement I
seeking pleasure on a kind of avoiding
the discomfort
is just increasing the confinement it's
still within the confinement it's still
with it's literally paying off a debt by
borrowing more money from somebody else
so you're just moving the debt around
while it is increasing and accumulating
so first you have to stop doing that I
you have to stop making it worse
and that is the beginning of samadhian
Mind development
virtue and sense restraint which would
then Reveal Your Own intentions
are you still trying to get rid of the
play the pain prolong the pleasure how
you still ignoring the neutral feeling
how you still want to activate oh now
that becomes apparent so now you can
actually not act out of that
and that's still the purification of the
mind it's the purification of your
intentions but exactly the confinement the pain the
but exactly the confinement the pain the
discomfort all of that it's not because
of these things are truly confining it's
because your mind
puts the sensuality and the pleasure and
the former ways of escaping first still
values it still assumes it still uses it
as a criteria in the reference point
so yes you can know why is that it
doesn't matter
what matters is that there is no first
point before which you were not sensual
or ignorant
it matches that that is your starting
point so if you undo it you won't be
going back to it because actually
as we said in previous talks nobody
wants sexuality to begin with
it's by not understanding that that's
why you are still putting it first and
very much Bound by it
because if you're not confined to begin
with with your feelings with the body
with your perceptions
what is that to seek the pleasure
instead of
when it's already quite not unpleasant
engaging with pleasure engaging with
scratching when there is no itch it's
actually why would I do that makes no
sense it's disturbing
it's disturbing
it's annoying it's a hassle it's
harassment